Inventory of the J.E. Morpurgo Papers 1937-2000
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Teaching materials, n.d., 1945-1970. (Box-folder 3:1-29)
  - Miscellaneous lecture materials and a copy of the examination in American Literature for the degree of B.A. in Two-Subjects, University of Leeds, May-June 1970., 12 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - J.E.M. essay on the American Civil War, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Untitled.
  - Occasional Lectures-to-go to Idaho, n.d., 1959-1961., 8 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
    1. The Continuing Use of English (1961; 4 pp.); 2. The Printed Word in Britain (1959; 5 pp.);3. Commencement Address (June 1961, 14 pp.); 4. Untitled, British-American relations (June 1966, 16 pp.); 5. Richer in Esteem: A Reappraisal of John Burgoyne (n.d., published, pp. 151-167);6. Untitled-English poetry (n.d., 25 pp.); 7. Forty Years On (n.d., 17 pp.); 8. Literature and Chauvinism: A Reconnaissance of Poetry of Canada and Australia (n.d., published essay, pp. 58-77).
  - J.E.M. essays and lectures on The Romantics, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
    1. The Irate St. Charles (n.d., 20 pp.); 2. Leigh Hunt (n.d., 14 pp.); 3. James Henry Leigh Hunt (n.d., 11 pp.).
  - J.E.M. lecture and notes: The Frontier, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - J.E.M. lecture: The Southern Tradition, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
    Outline for lecture.
  - J.E.M. essay/lecture: The Literature of Revolution, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - J.E.M.: Jazz, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:11)
  - J.E.M.: notes and book reviews on Canadian poetry, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 3:12)
  - J.E.M.: Social Context of Literature in the United States, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:13)
  - J.E.M.: Inaugural Lecture on American Literature, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:14)
    Includes introduction to lecture.
  - Lecture materials on James Fenimore Cooper, n.d. (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Lecture materials on e.e. cummings, n.d. (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Lecture materials-Emily Dickinson, n.d. (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Lecture materials-T.S. Eliot, n.d. (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Lecture materials on Ralph Waldo Emerson, n.d. (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Lecture materials on William Faulkner, n.d. (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Lecture materials on Robert Frost, n.d. (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Lecture materials on Nathaniel Hawthorne, n.d. (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Lecture materials on Henry James, n.d. (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Lecture materials on Herman Melville, n.d. (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Lecture materials on E.A. Robinson, Lindsay, Masters, and Sandburg, n.d. (Box-folder 3:25)
  - Lecture materials on Wallace Stevens, n.d. (Box-folder 3:26)
  - Lecture materials on Mark Twain, n.d. (Box-folder 3:27)
  - Lecture materials on William Carlos Williams, n.d. (Box-folder 3:28)
  - Lecture materials on Walt Whitman, n.d. (Box-folder 3:29)
  Series 7: Speeches
- Speeches, 1959-1976. (Box-folder 3:30-39)
  - J.E.M., Director's Speech for Valedictory, Unesco Regional Seminar, Madras, 19 December 1959., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:30)
  - J.E.M. speeches on Geo-politics, 1963., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:31)
    Includes Anglo-Israeli Project (20 pp.) and Speech at the Vienna Congress (8 pp.).
  - J.E.M. speeches and reports on Canada, 1964-1966., 6 items. (Box-folder 3:32)
  - J.E.M. sermon, 1972., 3 items. (Box-folder 3:33)
    Based on The Second Book of Samuel, delivered at Church Road Methodist Church, St. Annes-On-Sea (10 pp.). Includes bulletins.
  - J.E.M. draft of speech for Prize Day at Queens, Taunton, 1976., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:34)
  - J.E.M. speech on The Sicilian Vespers, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:35)
  - Speeches and commencement addresses, n.d., 1961-1967., 6 items. (Box-folder 3:36)
  - J.E.M. address for the awarding of a Doctor of Music degree to Charles Rosen, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:37)
  - J.E.M. drafts of Berlin Lecture, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:38)
  - J.E.M. address to Charles Lamb Society, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:39)
  Series 8: Papers relating to WW II and the military
- Papers relating to WW II and the military, n.d., 1944-1977. (Box-folder 4:1-11a)
  - J.E.M., Blueprint for War Memorials, 1945-1946., 3 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
    Draft and 2 published copies: Khaki and Blue, 1945; and News Bulletin, 1 May 1946.
  - J.E.M., The First of Foot, 6 September 1953., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:2)
    In: Scotland's Magazine (pp. 41-42).
  - J.E.M.: Chianti in Africa, April 1977., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
    In: Blackwood's Magazine (pp. 294-298). Includes letter to J.E.M. from David Fletcher regarding publication and payment.
  - J.E.M. notebook, n.d., 6 items. (Box-folder 4:4)
    Notebook with commentary and observations from World War II experiences. Written on the reverse of what appears to be an Italian account book. AMS. Also includes a draft of "Loot", by Seagull Minor, seemingly based on the notes (6 pp.).
  - J.E.M. essays on military regiments, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
    The First of Foot -The Royal Scots: Pontius Pilate's Bodyguard (9 pp.); The Lovat Scouts (6 pp.); The Dorset Regiment (4 pp.).
  - Unknown author, 139 Infantry Brigade, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:6)
    From Brigadier. Inscribed: This may interest you. It is one of my lesser literary efforts-but the easiest to get published. Signature illegible (1 p.).
  - Notes and essay on the 46th Division, n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 4:7)
    Published in Manchester Guardian, draft (4 pp.). Includes correspondence regarding a 1993 reunion of 46th Division officers.
  - J.E.M.: Q.E.D., n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:8)
    Published by Blackwood (pp. 495-497).
  - J.E.M. letter to Convoy, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:9)
    Re: British military service.
  - J.E.M.: Substantial Authority, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:10)
  - J.E.M.: Gin and Onion, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Certificate of J.E.M. membership in "Ye Ancient Order of Sea Dogs, 31 January 1941., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:11a)
    The certificate is signed on front and back by other members.
  Series 9: Articles
- Articles, n.d., 1932-1981. (Box-folder 4:12-59)
    Subseries 9.1: Articles regarding American-European relations
  - Articles regarding American-European relations, n.d., 1948-1981. (Box-folder 4:12-44)
    All articles in this sub-series have been written by J.E.M. unless otherwise mentioned.
    - Mid-Atlantic, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:12)
      Deals with the relationship between British and Americans in late 1930s-early 1940s. No publication title visible.
    - Myths, Half-Truths and History, October-November 1947., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:13)
      Published in: The English Speaking World (Pp. 738-743). Includes proofs.
    - Williamsburg, Virginia, Spring 1948., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:14)
      Published in: Transatlantic (pp. 25-31). Includes draft.
    - Speaking for Myself, April 1948., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:15)
      Published in Scots Review (p. 10).
    - West Country Looks West, Spring 1948., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:16)
      Published in: The West Country Magazine (pp. 19-21). Includes draft.
    - Darkest America on the British Map, 4 December 1949., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:17)
      Published in: The New York Times Magazine (pp. 22-29).
    - California's Sun in European Skies, 5 January 1950., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:18)
      Published in: The Listener (pp. 8-9). Includes draft.
    - Talking to Americans, 20 July 1950., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:19)
      Published in: The Listener (pp. 93-95).
    - Excerpts from: The Picket Line and Campfire Stories, A Collection of War Anecdotes Both Grave and Gay, Illustrative of the Triumphs and Trials of Soldier Life; With a Thousand and One Humorous Stories Told of and By Abraham Lincoln, Together with a Full Collection of Northern and Southern War Songs. By a Member of the G.A.R, [1951?]., 1 item (41 pp.). (Box-folder 4:20)
      Sent by R.B. Nye to J.E.M.
    - Untitled essay on poems, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 4:21)
      Essay discussed the following poems: Allen Tate's Ode to the Confederate Dead and Robert Lowell's Ode to the Union Dead. Includes copies of both poems.
    - Class Ridden America, 25 July 1952., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:22)
      Published in: John O. London.
    - The American Workshop, 20 August 1952., 1 items. (Box-folder 4:23)
      Published in: The Times Literary Supplement. No page number visible.
    - Jamestown, 15 May 1957., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:24)
      Published in: The Tatler and Bystander (pp. 364-365). Includes draft. Written to highlight Jamestown's 350th anniversary.
    - [Hysteria on Main Street], n.d. [195-?]., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:25)
      Section of an essay on British impressions of small-town America.
    - God's Almighty Railroad, May 1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:26)
      Published in: Quadrant (pp. 29-31). Includes version: God's Own Railroad.
    - Untitled address, 1981., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:27)
      Regards the subject of the 200th anniversary of the British surrender at Yorktown, Virginia.
    - From the Heart of an Anglo-American, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:28)
      Deals with England, America, and the Falkland Crisis.
    - Journey with Ghosts: A Personal Itinerary... that explores along the way the origin of Phi Beta Kappa, Summer 1995., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:29)
      Published in: Colonial Williamsburg Magazine (pp. 35-39).
    - The American Negro, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:30)
      Published essay, no publication title visible (pp. 16-24).
    - The Americans in Our Midst, n.d., 1 item (25 pp.). (Box-folder 4:31)
      Introduction to the Times Memorial volume to the Americans.
    - No More Cherry Trees, n.d., 1 item (15 pp.). (Box-folder 4:32)
    - Forty Years On, n.d., 1 item (17 pp.). (Box-folder 4:33)
      Observations on British-American relations.
    - View From Main Street, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:34)
      Observations on British-American relations (6 pp.). Includes AMS version (7 pp.)
    - Hollywood: America's Voice, n.d., 1 item (7pp.). (Box-folder 4:35)
    - The Clown in the Elsinore XV, n.d., 1 item (7 pp.). (Box-folder 4:36)
    - Essay and miscellaneous notes on American social structure and party system, n.d., 4 items (19 pp.). (Box-folder 4:37)
    - The American Election, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:38)
      Published in: Penguin Parade (pp. 112-124).
    - Untitled essay on 350th anniversary of the overseas Commonwealth, n.d., 1 item (5 pp.). (Box-folder 4:39)
      Deals with Jamestown, Yorktown, Williamsburg.
    - American Sports and Pastimes, n.d., 1 item (9 pp.). (Box-folder 4:40)
    - John Paul Jones: An American Hero, n.d., 1 item (4 pp.). (Box-folder 4:41)
    - British Service Publicity in the United States, n.d., 1 item (4 pp.). (Box-folder 4:42)
    - American Culture and Europe, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 4:43)
      Drafts and notes.
    - Miscellaneous lecture notes on British and American subjects, n.d., 11 items. (Box-folder 4:44)
    Subseries 9.2: Articles regarding British and European subjects
  - Articles regarding British and European subjects, 1932-1978. (Box-folder 4:45-59)
    All articles by J.E.M. unless otherwise noted.
    - Biographies for Britain, n.d., 1 item (5 pp.). (Box-folder 4:45)
    - Essays on Britain, n.d., 1964., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:46)
      Includes: Note on Britain - Second Class Power or Third Force (6 pp.); and an untitled essay on healthcare (9 pp.).
    - God's Almighty Nephew, n.d., 1 item (8 pp.). (Box-folder 4:47)
      Essay on Richard Brothers.
    - Untitled essay on Michael St. Denis, n.d., 1 item (4 pp.). (Box-folder 4:48)
    - The 'Ardent Spirit ' of Old Moscow, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:49)
      Published in: The Compleat Imbiber (pp. 17-19).
    - Untitled lecture draft, n.d., 1 item (20 pp.). (Box-folder 4:50)
      Deals with the lives of young British royalty. Focus on Queen Victoria and twentieth-century Princesses Elizabeth and Margaret.
    - Pleasure Resorts of the Eighteenth-Century In and Around London, 1932., 1 item (7 pp.). (Box-folder 4:51)
      Essay draft.
    - In Defense of the King, 4 August 1950., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:52)
      Published in: Public Opinion (pp. 2-3).
    - The Way to Travel in Comfort, 15 April 1953., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:53)
      Published in: The Tatler and Bystander (pp.166, 170).
    - Who Will Succeed Churchill?, September 1953., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:54)
      Published in: Mayfair (3 pp.).
    - Various essays in the "Report from London" series, October 1953-July 1954., 8 items. (Box-folder 4:55)
      Published in: Mayfair.
    - Rugger-The Manly Sport For Wives, 3 October 1956., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:56)
      Published in: The Tatler and Bystander (pp. 16-17).
    - A Little Bit Sentimental, 1961., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:57)
      2 versions.
    - Congress of Vienna - 1963 Style, 1964., 1 item (4 pp.). (Box-folder 4:58)
      Was to be published in Books, January/February 1964.
    - Richer in Esteem: A Reappraisal of John Burgoyne, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:59)
      A tribute to Russel Nye publihsed by Michigan State University Press (pp. 151-167).
  Series 10: Papers relating to the history of the book - readers, writers, publishers
- Papers relating to the history of the book - readers, writers, publishers, n.d., 1950-1981. (Box-folder 5:1-23)
  - Essays on books, reading, and publishing in Britain, 1950s., 25 items. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - The Price of Books, 8 December 1955., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:2)
    Published in: London Calling (p. 16).
  - Some Notes on Popular Publishing Experience in the United Kingdom, 1956., 1 item (18 pp.). (Box-folder 5:3)
    Prepared for the UNESCO regional meeting on the Production of Reading Material for New Literates, held in Pakistan.
  - Essays and speeches on book history, 1956-1985., 6 items. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Books for the New Reading Public, March 1958., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:5)
    Published in: The Unesco Courier (p. 26).
  - The Printed Word in Britain, 1959., 1 item (5 pp.). (Box-folder 5:6)
  - British Books at Large, October 1960., 1 item (8 pp.). (Box-folder 5:7)
    Published in: English Language Teaching.
  - The World as Oyster, 1962., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:8)
    Reprinted from: The Penrose Annual (Vol. 56., pp. 41-46).
  - Libel and Copyright, n.d., 1 item (13 pp.). (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Speeches on children and reading, 1964-1965., 3 items. (Box-folder 5:10)
    Includes: Children Reading in the Age of Television (10 p.); Osborne Library (9 pp.); and untitled (2 pp.).
  - The Publishing Problem - a Kite for policy makers, 1965., 4 items (8 pp.). (Box-folder 5:11)
    Includes correspondence with the Journal of Documentation regarding publication.
  - Books and Libraries in an Industrial Society, 1968., 2 items. (Box-folder 5:12)
    Paper presented at 34th Session of the IFLA General Trust; published in IFLA-Communications-FIAB (pp. 223-229). Includes draft (13 pp.).
  - Commentary from J.E.M. on Cameron Hazelhurst's Being Discreet About the Dead - Some Problems for Biographers, February 1978., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:13)
    Includes excerpt on Hazelhurst's work. Published in the Quadrant (pp. 4-5).
  - A Prospect of Paperbacks, 1981., 1 item (9 pp.). (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Paperbacks to the Wall, January-February 1981., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:15)
    Published in: Quadrant (pp. 18-21).
  - The National Book League and the Future of Books, [1956?]., 1 item (4 pp.). (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Books to Own: An Adventure in Publishing, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:17)
    Published in: Review 46 (pp. 39-43).
  - Miscellaneous notes on an essay about editing, n.d., 1 item (22 pp.). (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Untitled essay on British and American newspaper buying and reading, n.d., 1 item (2 pp.). (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Supplication to St. John Stevas, n.d., 1 item (6 pp.). (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Is There A Future for the Written Word?, n.d., 1 item (12 pp.). (Box-folder 5:21)
  - Making Books There is No End, n.d., 1 item (63 pp.). (Box-folder 5:22)
    Draft essay, includes bibliographic notes.
  - Speech on the National Book League, n.d., 1 item (9 pp.). (Box-folder 5:23)
  Series 11: Papers related to Penguin Publishing
- Papers related to Penguin Publishing, n.d., 1947-1985. (Box-folder 5:24-44)
  - Newspaper clippings regarding the second series of Penguin Parade, 1947., 4 items. (Box-folder 5:24)
  - Correspondence concerning the Anglo-American Historical Conference and other matters relating to Pelican Histories, 1951., 30 items. (Box-folder 5:25)
  - Correspondence concerning the Penguin Modern History of China, 1951., 24 items. (Box-folder 5:26)
  - Correspondence concerning Penguin History of England, 1951-1957., 54 items. (Box-folder 5:27)
  - Correspondence concerning Pelican Histories Series, 1951-1959., 69 items. (Box-folder 5:28)
  - Correspondence concerning the Penguin History of Modern France, 1951-1959., 55 items. (Box-folder 5:29)
  - Correspondence concerning Penguin History of India, 1951-1960., 22 items. (Box-folder 5:30)
  - Correspondence concerning Pelican Histories series, 1951-1960., 89 items. (Box-folder 5:31)
    Includes correspondence with authors, acceptance and rejection letters, and proposals for histories of Rome, Russia, Scotland, Spain, and Portugal.
  - Correspondence concerning editing and production of Junior History of England series, 1952-1956., 71 items. (Box-folder 5:32)
  - Correspondence concerning Penguin Books, Ltd., 1952-1957., 33 items. (Box-folder 5:33)
  - Correspondence concerning Penguin History of Japan, 1952-1959., 54 items. (Box-folder 5:34)
  - Correspondence concerning Penguin History of the Church of England, 1952-1960., 30 items. (Box-folder 5:35)
  - Correspondence relating to Penguin Books, including Pelican Histories, 1952-1960., 147 items. (Box-folder 5:36)
  - Correspondence concerning publication of Penguin History of the Royal Navy, 1953-1956., 35 items. (Box-folder 5:37)
  - Correspondence concerning the publication of The History of the Catholic Church, by Father Kevin Booth, 1953-1957., 36 items. (Box-folder 5:38)
  - Correspondence concerning publication of the Penguin History of New Zealand, 1953-1958., 27 items. (Box-folder 5:39)
  - J.E.M., Untitled essay on Penguin publishing. 1956., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:40)
  - J..E.M., The King and I,., 1 item. (Box-folder 5:41)
    Essay on Pelican chief-of-staff Allen Lane, Blackwood's (pp. 480-487).
  - Colin Campbell, Penguins had 'no right' to succeed, 3 January 1985., 1 item (1 p.). (Box-folder 5:42)
    Article from Australian newspaper on the subject of Penguin books, Townsville Bulletin.
  - Illustrations for Penguin Junior History of England series, n.d., 12 items. (Box-folder 5:43)
  - J.E.M., Once Upon A Time, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 5:44)
    Penguin Progress 13, (pp. 33-37). Includes TMS of article, (6 pp.).
  Series 12: Essays on Literature
- Essays on Literature, n.d., 1930-1985. (Box-folder 6:1-32)
  All essays by J.E.M., unless otherwise mentioned.
  - Poet-Prophet of America, 31 July 1953., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:1)
    Essay on Walt Whitman, in The Times Literary Supplement (p. 492).
  - Essays on literature, arts, and sciences in Britain, 1930-1958., 5 items. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Herman Melville and England, 1950., 2 items (Box-folder 6:3)
    In: The Month (pp. 180-186). Includes TMS draft (14 pp.)
  - Romantic Pirate: Edward John Trelawny, 1952., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:4)
    Introduction to Trelawny's last Days of Shelley and Byron. London: Folio Society (pp. iii-xvii).
  - Essays on English language, 1958, 1961., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:5)
    Nonsense and the English (7 pp.); and The Continuing Use of English (4 pp.).
  - 'from that damnable place'-The Englishness of American Literature, 1971., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:6)
    Inaugural lecture at University of Leeds. Published in University of Leeds Review (pp. 69-87). Includes TMS draft (36 pp.).
  - Essays from Contemporary Novelists, 1972., 5 items. (Box-folder 6:7)
    1. Robertson Davies; 2. Robert (Ranke) Graves; 3. A(lfred) B(ertram) Guthrie, Jr.; 4. Eric (Robert Russell) Linklater; 5. (John) Hugh MacLennan.
  - Damned from Here to Eternity, November 1979., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:8)
    Essay on Rudyard Kipling published in Quadrant (pp. 54-56). Includes TMS draft (8 pp).
  - William McCann,(Austin) Merrill Moore, 1980., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:9)
    Dictionary of American Biography, Supplement Six (no place; pp. 461-462).
  - Draft essay on biography as a literary form., n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:10)
    Relates to work on Barnes Wallis published in 1981.
  - Keats Memorial Lecture: The Poet and Barabbas: Keats, His Publishers and Editors, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:11)
    Given at Guy's Hospital for the Royal College of Surgeons, Guy's Hospital, and the Worshipful Society of Apothecaries.
  - Untitled essay on literature, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:12)
  - What is Poetry?, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:13)
    Incomplete essay.
  - Speech on poetry in America, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:14)
  - Essay on American literature, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:15)
  - American Literature and Britain, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:16)
  - Draft of Introductory presentation in American Literature, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:17)
  - Essay on American literature, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:18)
  - Expatriation and the frontier in American literature, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:19)
    Draft essay.
  - Philosophocide, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:20)
    Essay on William Godwin.
  - The Mississippi, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:21)
  - Text of a lecture delivered to the Creative Writing Group at the University of Iowa, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:22)
  - Literary Independence, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:23)
  - Joyce Cary, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:24)
  - Essays on Edward John Trelawny's Romantic Pirate, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 6:25)
  - Essay on literature in post-World War II England, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:26)
  - Essay on Christopher Marlowe, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:27)
  - Essay on Goronwy Owen, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:28)
  - Essay on English language literature, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:29)
  - Bigraphical notes on literary figures, n.d., 7 items. (Box-folder 6:30)
    Entries on literary figures for unidentified reference work: Blunden, Lamb, MacLennan, Burgoyne, and Davies. Also includes a draft essay on Leigh Hunt.
  - Bibliographies on American literature and civilization, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 6:31)
  - Escape from Fuddy-Duddy, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:32)
  Series 13: Book reviews
- Book reviews, n.d., 1938-1980. (Box-folder 6:33-54)
  All reviews by J.E.M., unless otherwise mentioned.
  - Review of Matthew Cooper's The German Army, 1933-1945, 1978., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:33)
    Also includes letter from Literary Editor of Yorkshire Post requesting a copy of the review as well as a letter from Cooper thanking J.E.M. for the review.
  - Review of Bertrand Russell's Our Knowledge of the External World, 1938., 1 item. (Box-folder 6:34)
  - Book reviews published in various newspapers and journals, n.d., 1946-1947., 36 items. (Box-folder 6:35)
    Places of publication include: The Times Literary Supplement, Books of the Month, Tribune, Time and Tide, Birmingham Post, and others.
  - Book reviews published in various newspapers and journals, 1948-1952., 78 items. (Box-folder 6:36)
    Places of publication include: The Times Literary Supplement, Books of the Month, Tribune, and others. Some are identified as written by J.E.M., others are not. Includes some reviews written by Jonathan More.
  - Various book reviews on American literature, published in The Times Literary Supplement, ca. 1952-1953., 9 items. (Box-folder 6:37)
    Titles and authors of books reviewed are listed on the front of the folder.
  - Review of Eric Linklater's Fanfare for a Tin Hat, ca. 1970., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:38)
    Includes letter from Linklater to J.E.M.